Petr Stepanov

UI/UX designer. Frontend and desktop developer.

Summary of Qualifications

Ph.D. graduate in physics with 5+ year expertise in user interface (UI) and user experience (UX) design. Strong web application and desktop software development skills. Authorized to work in the US on Optional Practical Training (OPT expires February 2023). Will consider visa sponsorship offers.

Work Experience

C++ Software Developer

Thomas Jefferson National Laboratory (JLab), Newport News, VA, USA.

Jul 2020 - Current

Software Developer • Postdoctoral Researcher

<u>Catholic University of America (CUA)</u>, Washington, DC, USA.

Jul 2020 - Current

Software Developer • Research Assistant

Bowling Green State University (BGSU), Bowling Green, OH, USA.

Aug 2014 - May 2020

- Wrote three desktop GUI programs for spectra fitting and interpretation (C++, CMake, ROOT, Qt, Java)
 - GitHub repositories contain over 10k lines of code in total: <u>TLIST Processor</u>, <u>SW Calculator</u>, <u>RooPositron</u>.
 - Technologies used: CMake, C++, ROOT, Fox GUI and RooFit libraries.
 - Extended default ROOT GUI library (Qt-based) to support the MVP design pattern.

UI/UX Designer, Frontend Developer • Freelance

Sep 2012 - Current

- Designed and built online e-commerce store <u>Sticker Store LLC</u> with static website generator (Figma, Hexo, Snipcart, Bootstrap, SASS, EJS, Node.js).
 - Improved the Google PageSpeed Insights metrics (CLS, LCP) up to 97%.
 - Created a recursive script to export over 300 products from YAML file to Google Merchant.
 - Optimized SEO. Project reached over 1400 organic monthly users.
- Made iOS application (Swift, Ulkit, storyboards) for the <u>We.Team</u> messenger (more than 3k monthly downloads in AppStore). Participated in cloud-based messenger development with enhanced file sharing capabilities (HTML, React JS, SASS).
- Migrated the landing page for <u>Sweetbridge</u> company from WordPress to Jekyll static site generator (Ruby, CSS). This resulted in a 70% improvement in the page load time.
- Developed the front-end part (Angular.js, HTML, LESS) for Lili Social network.
 - Assisted with iOS mobile application (Ionic).
 - Enabled SEO crawling of over 1000 Angular.js pages with Google bot.
- · Web design.
 - Designed logos, UI/UX prototypes (Figma, Sketch, Illustrator) and branding identity for over <u>10 different</u> companies.
 - Converted numerous design assets and mockups into responsive HTML and CSS.
 - Mocked up and integrated dozens of cross-browser responsive email templates.

Web Designer, Full Stack Web Developer

Gridnine Systems, Moscow, Russia.

Apr 2011 - Aug 2014

Prototyped and designed interactive mockups for <u>Otixo</u> cloud file integrator (Balsamiq, Adobe Creative Suite).
Utilized Google Web Toolkit (GWT) Model-View-Presenter (MVP) framework to develop application frontend

(JavaScript, responsive CSS).

- Responsible for the front-end development of the <u>ATH American Express</u> the largest travel management company in Russia (JavaScript, Backbone.js, and RequireJS). Increased the front-end load time by over 30%.
- Implemented image processing servlets on the backend to generate banners for five different social networks (PHP, ImageMagic).
- Wireframed and sliced to web pages numerous UI/UX mockups for web applications (Balsamiq, Photoshop, HTML and CSS).

Computer Science Teacher

Phys-Tech College at MIPT, Moscow, Russia.

Oct 2009 - May 2011

 Provided instructions and guidance to high school students on following computer courses: C/C++ programming, HTML, Adobe Photoshop and 3D Studio Max.

Research Scientist

<u>Institute for Theoretical and Experimental Physics (ITEP)</u>, Moscow, Russia.

Sep 2008 - Apr 2011

 Application of positron lifetime spectroscopy for studying the radioactive-induced defects in steels. Monte-Carlo particle simulations with Fortran 95. Maintaining software for CAMECA tomographic atom probe (MSVC). Application of CERN ROOT libraries for fitting and analysis of experimental spectra.

Education

Bowling Green State University (BGSU) • Ohio, USA

Aug 2014 - May 2020

Ph.D. in Photochemical Sciences • GPA 3.423. Novel developments in positron annihilation spectroscopy techniques—from experimental setups to advanced processing software. <u>View manuscript</u>.

British Higher School of Art and Design (BHSAD) • Moscow, Russia

Dec 2011 - Feb 2012

Three-month intensive in Graphical Design and Visual Communications. Lectures and hands-on experience in graphic design. Intensive covered following subjects: brand identity, illustration principles, typography and lettering, effective advertising campaigns.

Computer Science Skills

- **Essentials**. Git, SVN, SSH, Linux, and Terminal usage. BASH scripting. IDEs: Eclipse, Xcode, Visual Studio Code (VS Code). Project management: JIRA, Trello.
- **Desktop app development**. C/C++, GNU make, CMake. Frameworks: Qt, CERN ROOT, Geant4. Java and Swing. Python.
- **Frontend**: HTML, CSS (LESS and SASS), Bootstrap, responsive web design, JavaScript and jQuery, npm, gulp, AngularJS, React.js. Google Web Toolkit. PHP and WordPress themes development.
- Backend. Node.js, EJS, Java.
- **UI/UX design**. Figma, Sketch, InVision Studio, Adobe XD, Adobe Photoshop, Adobe Illustrator, Inkscape, Blasamiq, Blender.
- Apple iOS. Fundamental Swift skills. User interface development with Ulkit and storyboards.

Professional Networks

- Discover my professional contacts on LinkedIn (200+ connections).
- Find examples of my code on GitHub (50+ repositories).
- Check out my UI design portfolio on <u>Dribbble</u> (50+ shots).